# Matthew L. Leavitt, PhD

+1 925 575 7628 | matthew@mleavitt.net | mleavitt.net

Passionate about understanding, explaining, and advancing synthetic and biological intelligence.

#### Research Interests

My primary research interest is furthering the science of deep learning—developing and conducting rigorous, empirical experiments to better understand deep learning systems—and using the resulting insights to improve the performance, efficiency, and human-interpretability of these systems.

#### Education \_

**McGill University** Montréal, Québec, Canada

PHD IN PHYSIOLOGY 2011 - 2017

- Area of specialization: Computational & systems cognitive neuroscience
- Advisor: Prof. Julio C. Martinez-Trujillo, MD, PhD
- Dissertation Title: Network properties underlying working memory in primate prefrontal cortex

**McGill University** Montréal, Québec, Canada

BSc Major in Neuroscience, Minor in Musical Science and Technology

• Focus: Cognitive and behavioral neuroscience (Major); Digital Signal Processing, synthesis, and sampling (Minor)

### Professional Experience \_\_\_\_\_\_

**AI Resident** Menlo Park, California, USA

FACEBOOK AI RESEARCH (FAIR)

August 2019 - February 2021

2006 - 2010

- The FAIR AI residency brings individuals with non-traditional backgrounds into AI research by pairing them with FAIR researchers to identify and solve novel AI problems.
- · Led a series of projects under the supervision of Ari Morcos examining how human-intuitive representations in deep networks affect generalization and robustness, and the state of interpretability research, leading to three first-author manuscripts.
- · Initiated and continue to collaborate on multiple projects attempting to improve transformer models for vision tasks, which have thus far generated one publication.
- · Implemented vision transformers and a number of other features in vissl, FAIR's open-source toolbox for self-supervised learning.

#### **Postdoctoral Research Fellow**

CUSEC

London, Ontario, & Montréal,

Québec, Canada

UNIVERSITY OF WESTERN ONTARIO - MARTINEZ-TRUJILLO COGNITIVE NEUROPHSYIOLOGY LAB

July 2017 - April 2019

Led a research project examining the neuronal dynamics of rule learning in prefrontal cortex in macaque monkeys.

## **Member, Board of Advisors**

Montréal, Québec, Canada

CANADIAN UNIVERSITY SOFTWARE ENGINEERING CONFERENCE (CUSEC)

2015-present

- CUSEC (www.cusec.net) is an annual, three-day, student-run software engineering and computer science conference.
- · Provide guidance and mentorship to the Conference Chairs and staff.
- Collaborate to shape the priorities of CUSEC: ensuring the longevity and integrity of the organization and its mission.

**Conference Co-Chair** Montréal, Québec, Canada

• Recruited and enabled a staff of 23 across 7 teams (logistics, sponsorship, speakers, design, promotions, events, and A/V).

- Coordinated hospitality for and managed relationships with ~600 attendees (500 students, 18 speakers, dozens of sponsor representatives, and staff).

MATTHEW L. LEAVITT, PHD · CURRICULUM VITAE

CUSEC 2012 - 2013

- I directed the content, and recruited and hosted the ~18 speakers for two consecutive conferences.
- Notable speakers included Alexis Ohanian, co-founder of Reddit; Bret Victor, interface designer, whose invited talk, *Inventing On Principle*, has 800k+ views on Vimeo and YouTube; and Benjamin Black, who co-conceptualized Amazon Web Services.

#### Skills \_

#### **Quantitative & Technical**

- · Research techniques for deep neural networks
  - Noteworthy example: Devised a novel regularizer to examine the causal role of easily interpretable neurons in deep neural networks (Leavitt and Morcos (2021) ICLR).
- · Machine learning & statistical techniques for high-dimensional neural data
  - Noteworthy example: Decoding the contents of working memory from large networks of simultaneously-recorded neurons in prefrontal cortex in macaque monkeys (Leavitt et al. (2017) PNAS & Leavitt et al. (2017) Cerebral Cortex).
- · Modeling of neural, biological, and behavioral systems
- Expertise in scientific and numerical programming languages including Python and MATLAB
  - Noteworthy example (PyTorch): I contributed a number of features to vissl, FAIR's open-source toolbox for self-supervised learning, including vision transformers, new data augmentations, and gradient clipping.
- · Experimental design for neuroscientific, psychological, and psychophysical research
- · Neurosurgical techniques for research in non-human primates
- · Digital signal processing for audio and neurophysiological applications

#### **Communication & Organization**

- · Oral, written, and graphic communication, with a particular passion for scientific and technical content
  - Noteworthy examples (oral): I have received numerous awards for oral presentations given to both general audiences and other neuroscientists (see my comprehensive CV at **mleavitt.net**), and delivered conference presentations and course lectures on behalf of my supervisor.
  - Noteworthy example (written): Starting in 2014, I was uniquely tasked with editing every manuscript and grant proposal produced by my doctoral lab.
- · Leadership, vision, management, logistics, content production, and vendor relations
  - Noteworthy example: See my Professional Experience with CUSEC.
- · Scientific & technical literature review
  - Noteworthy example: Leavitt et al. (2017, Trends in Neurosciences) reviews the evidence for working memory-related neural activity across different brain regions.
- Teaching across diverse fields (neuroscience, music production, mathematics) and pupils (elementary through university-age students, macaque monkeys)

#### Creative

- · Writing and editing for comedy on stage and in print
- 17 years experience in music production, engineering, and composition
- 20 years experience playing drums in a variety of genres and contexts
- Digital, 35mm, and medium format photography
- Carpentry and woodworking

## Publications, Conference Presentations, and Peer-review \_

I published three first-author and one contributing-author deep learning research manuscripts after only  $\sim$ 1.5 years in the field, and six peer-reviewed neuroscience articles (including one review article). I have also given dozens of oral presentations at a range of scientific conferences and seminars. For my comprehensive CV, a link to my Google Scholar profile, and lay publication summaries, see **mleavitt.net**. The remainder of my CV details my peer-review experience, publications, and presentations.

## Scientific peer-review (ad hoc) \_\_\_

International Conference on Machine Learning, Nature Neuroscience, Neuron, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, Nature Communications, Cerebral Cortex, The Journal of Neuroscience, Experimental Brain Research, Frontiers in Neural Circuits

## **Publications and Preprints**

#### **ConViT: Improving Vision Transformers with Soft Convolutional Inductive Biases**

arXiv (2021)

Under review at an archival venue

S d'Ascoli, H Touvron, ML Leavitt, AS Morcos, G Biroli, L Sagun

#### Selectivity considered harmful: evaluating the causal impact of class selectivity in DNNs

International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) (2021 - Accepted)

Also appears in ICML Workshop on Human Interpretability in Machine Learning (2020)

ML Leavitt, AS Morcos

#### Towards falsifiable interpretability research

NeurIPS Workshop: ML Retrospectives, Surveys & Meta-Analyses (2020)

ML Leavitt, AS Morcos

#### Linking average-and worst-case perturbation robustness via class selectivity and dimensionality

arXiv (2020)

Under review at an archival venue

Also appears in ICML workshop on Uncertainty and Robustness in Deep Learning (2020)

ML Leavitt, AS Morcos

#### A normalization circuit underlying coding of spatial attention in primate lateral prefrontal cortex

eNeuro (2019)

LR Duong, ML Leavitt, F Pieper, A Sachs, JC Martinez-Trujillo

#### Sustained activity encoding working memories: not fully distributed

Trends in Neurosciences (2017)

ML Leavitt, D Mendoza-Halliday, JC Martinez-Trujillo

#### Correlated variability modifies working memory fidelity in primate prefrontal neuronal ensembles

Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (2017)

ML Leavitt, F Pieper, AJ Sachs, JC Martinez-Trujillo

#### A quadrantic bias in prefrontal representation of visual-mnemonic space

Cerebral Cortex (2017)

ML Leavitt, F Pieper, AJ Sachs, JC Martinez-Trujillo

#### Single-trial decoding of intended eye movement goals from lateral prefrontal cortex neural ensembles

Journal of Neurophysiology (2015)

CB Boulay, F Pieper, M Leavitt, J Martinez-Trujillo, AJ Sachs

## Structure of spike count correlations reveals functional interactions between neurons in dorsolateral prefrontal cortex area 8a of behaving primates

PLoS ONE (2013)

ML Leavitt, F Pieper F, A Sachs, R Joober, JC Martinez-Trujillo

#### Press \_

#### Easy-to-interpret neurons may hinder learning in deep neural networks

Facebook AI Research Blog (2020)

#### US travel ban blocking students from presenting their research

Ars Technica (2018)

#### This neuroscientist's poster showed how US travel bans stifle groundbreaking research

Quartz (2018)

## Conference Presentations \_\_\_\_\_

## TALKS/LECTURES

2020	Selectivity considered harmful: evaluating the causal impact of class selectivity in DNNs,  ML Leavitt, AS Morcos  NeuroMatch	Neuromatch.io
2019	Network properties underlying cognition in macaque LPFC,  ML Leavitt Invited talk, Blake Richards Lab	University of Toronto, Toronto, ON
2018	Ensemble mechanisms of rule learning in primate prefrontal cortex,  ML Leavitt, C Boulay, LR Duong, RA Gulli, AJ Sachs, JC Martinez-Trujillo.  Nanosymposium on Decision Making: Circuits and Computations	Society for Neuroscience, San Diego, CA
2018	Ensemble mechanisms of rule learning in primate prefrontal cortex,  ML Leavitt Invited talk, Xiao-Jing Wang Lab	New York University, New York, NY
2018	Network properties underlying cognition in LPFC,  ML Leavitt  Invited talk, Roozbeh Kiani Lab	New York University, New York, NY
2017	Correlated variability modifies working memory fidelity in primate prefrontal neuronal ensembles, <u>ML Leavitt</u> Neuroscience and Biology Group	MILA, Montréal, QC
2017	<b>Correlated variability modifies working memory fidelity in primate prefrontal neuronal ensembles</b> , ML Leavitt, AJ Sachs, JC Martinez-Trujillo. Workshop on Error-based learning in short-term and episodic memory	Computational and Systems Neuroscience (COSYNE), Snowbird, UT
2016	Heterogeneous effects of neuronal ensemble size, tuning, and correlation structure on the decoding of spatial working memory in dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, ML Leavitt, AJ Sachs, JC Martinez-Trujillo. Session on Visual Memory: Neural Mechanisms	Vision Sciences Society, St. Pete's Beach, FL
2016	Noise correlation structure shapes ensemble coding of working memory in prefrontal cortex, ML Leavitt, F Pieper, AJ Sachs, JC Martinez-Trujillo.  Nanosymposium on Spatial Attention and Working Memory	Society for Neuroscience, San Diego, CA
2015	Correlated variability and the fidelity of prefrontal working memory representations, ML Leavitt, AJ Sachs, JC Martinez-Trujillo. Nanosymposium on Learning and Memory	Society for Neuroscience, Chicago, IL
2014	<b>Noise correlations and coding during spatial working memory</b> , ML Leavitt, JC Martinez-Trujillo. Satellite Symposium on Primate Brain Circuits and Behavior	Canadian Association for Neuroscience, Montreal, QC
2012	The relation between local field potentials and single units across a microelectrode array implanted in macaque dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, AJ Sachs, KJ Miller, F Pieper, ML Leavitt, JC Martinez-Trujillo. Nanosymposium on Signal Propagation	Society for Neuroscience, New Orleans, LA

## Posters

2020	Selectivity considered harmful: evaluating the causal impact of class selectivity in DNNs,  ML Leavitt, AS Morcos	BayLearn, San Francisco, CA
2018	<b>Learning-related modulation of rule representation in primate prefrontal cortex ensembles</b> , <u>Leavitt ML</u> , Boulay C, Gulli RA, Duong LR, Sachs A, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Neuroinformatics, Montréal, QC
2017	Prefrontal cortex ensemble activity during during associative visuomotor rule learning in primates, Leavitt ML, Boulay C, Gulli RA, Duong LR, Sachs A, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Society for Neuroscience, Washington, DC
2017	Lateral prefrontal cortex single neuron and ensemble activity during associative learning in virtually navigating monkeys, Duong LR, Gulli RA, Corrigan BW, Leavitt ML, Doucet G, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Society for Neuroscience, Washington, DC
2017	<b>Hippocampal single neuron and ensemble activity during associative learning in virtually navigating primates</b> , Gulli RA, Duong LR, Corrigan BW, Doucet G, Leavitt ML, Williams S, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Society for Neuroscience, Washington, DC
2017	Correlated variability modifies working memory fidelity in primate prefrontal neuronal ensembles, <u>Leavitt ML</u> , Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Canadian Association for Neuroscience, Montréal, QC
2016	Beyond the single neuron: Ensemble coding of working memory in primate prefrontal cortex, Leavitt ML, Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC	The Future of Visual Attention, Rochester, NY
2016	Non-selective neurons contribute information to neuronal ensembles by modifying noise correlation structure, Leavitt ML, Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Canadian Association for Neuroscience, Toronto, ON
2015	<b>Predicting decision outcomes from single realizations of lateral prefrontal cortex neuronal activity</b> , Boulay C, <u>Leavitt ML</u> , Pieper F, Martinez-Trujillo JC, Sachs A	Society for Neuroscience, Chicago, IL
2015	Neural representation of spatial working memory is divided into quadrants in primate prefrontal cortex, Leavitt ML, Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Canadian Association for Neuroscience, Vancouver, BC
2014	Neural tuning affects spike-rate correlations during a spatial working memory task, Leavitt ML, Pieper F, Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Society for Neuroscience, Washington, DC
2014	<b>Single-trial dorsolateral prefrontal cortex neural trajectories predict intended saccade direction</b> , Boulay C, Pieper F, <u>Leavitt ML</u> , Martinez-Trujillo JC, Sachs AJ	Society for Neuroscience, Washington, DC
2014	Correlated spiking during during spatial working memory in macaque prefrontal area 8a, Leavitt ML, Pieper F, Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Canadian Association for Neuroscience, Montreal, QC
2013	Anti-correlated spike rates associated with working memory activity in macaque dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, Leavitt ML, Pieper F, Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Society for Neuroscience, San Diego, CA
2013	Spike count correlation variability in visual, presaccadic, and visuopresaccadic neurons of macaque dorsolateral prefrontal cortex during a working memory task, Leavitt ML, Pieper F, Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Canadian Association for Neuroscience, Toronto, ON
2012	Spike rate correlations in visual, presaccadic, and visuopresaccadic neurons in area 8a of macaque prefrontal cortex during a spatial working memory task, Leavitt ML, Pieper F, Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Society for Neuroscience, New Orleans, LA
2012	<b>Spike rate correlations vary by neuron response type during working memory in macaque prefrontal area 8A</b> , <u>Leavitt ML</u> , Pieper F, Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Canadian Association for Neuroscience, Vancouver, BC
2012	Spike count correlations in visual, visuomotor, and motor neurons of macaque prefrontal area 8A during working memory maintenance, Leavitt ML, Pieper F, Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC <sub>MATTHEW L. LEAVITT, PHD · CURRICULUM VITAE</sub>	Vision Science Society, Naples, FL 5

2011	Correlated activity of dorsolateral prefrontal cortex neurons during spatial	Society for Neuroscience,
	working memory maintenance, <u>Leavitt ML</u> , Pieper F, Sachs AJ, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Washington, DC
2011	Spike rate correlations between primate dorsolateral prefrontal cortex neurons during a spatial working memory task, <u>Leavitt ML</u> , Schneiderman M, Martinez-Trujillo JC	Canadian Association for Neuroscience, Quebec, QC
2011	Spike count correlations between primate dorsolateral prefrontal cortex neurons during a spatial working memory task, Martinez-Trujillo JC, Leavitt ML, Schneiderman M	Vision Sciences Society, Naples, FL